Okay.
Good evening.
Thank you to everybody who is able to join us tonight.
Looks like we've got a big crowd.
That's great.
I'm sure we'll have a few more people joining us as we get started.
For those of you who haven't met, I'm Dave.
I'm the principal here at the school.
We got a good team from the school here to share lots of important information with you.
To give you a bit of context, this is the third year we've done this format.
We've received a lot of positive feedback over the years.
Originally started as a real focus on grade 12s.
And then what we heard from parents over and over and over again was, wow, that would have
been great information to have in grade 9, 10, or 11.
So we're thrilled that we have people joining us from across the grades.
Most of this information will be most relevant to students in 10, 11, or 12.
But that doesn't mean that there isn't something there for everybody.
And maybe we'll allow for some questions for you to start thinking about that you might
want to ask counselors, career programs, advanced placement, scholarship contacts, those sort
of things in the months or years ahead.
So depending on where you're joining us from, you know, most of us are here gathered on
the traditional territories of the Coast Salish people, the Musqueam, the Tsleil-Waututh,
and the Squamish, on whose traditional territories we teach, learn, and live.
I see that we've got a few more folks joining us.
So I'm just going to hit pause again for another minute.
We'll get everybody in and then we're going to start with the formal component of the evening.
Okay.
I think we've got most, if not everybody in now.
So to give you a sense of what we're going to go through tonight, we're going to talk
a lot about grad requirements, post-secondary requirements, give you some information about
what that process looks like.
We're also going to spend some time looking and talking about scholarships and how you
find out information about scholarships, the kind of scholarships that are available to
you, advanced placement programs, and then the massive range of careers programs and
industry training connections that we offer at Burnaby Mountain and across Burnaby in
general.
One of the things that we're not going to talk about specifically, but just to kind
of keep in the background is that when we're talking about building a portfolio, we're
talking about a post-secondary portfolio that could be for university, it could be for college,
but it's also for the workplace or anything else that you want to pursue.
And so some of the things that are up on the screen now are things that are going to apply
to any and all of those things.
So obviously, good grades, strong academics, and exposure to a diverse and rigorous curriculum
is going to be a component of what any post-secondary plan is going to involve.
Obviously, grades in areas that you're wanting to pursue or wanting to continue need to be
a priority.
As you start applying for post-secondaries, we'll talk about this a little bit later,
but specific, honest, and well-written statements.
So just start thinking about your passions, your values, your interests, and thinking
about how you're going to craft that for post-secondaries.
I'm just going to hit pause for a second.
I'm getting a lot of people requesting to record.
You're welcome to record.
I'll hit accept in a second.
We're also going to post this information up on the school website tomorrow, so don't
feel like you've got to capture everything as we're going.
So back to the slide, lots of information about or lots of value placed from post-secondaries
around extracurricular involvement.
Mountain offers a ton of options for you, so we'll talk a bit about that.
As we go, volunteering, letters of recommendation.
I know Miss Bellier will talk about letters of recommendation when she's talking about
scholarships.
Obviously, having adults in the building who know students as learners and can speak to
and support some of the characteristics that we think are going to do them well when they
move on to post-secondary is something you want to highlight in a post-secondary portfolio.
Work experience is going to come up a little bit later on, particularly jobs related to
the area that you're looking at applying to.
And then just in general, sort of those core competencies around leadership, innovation,
initiative, creativity, and community contributions are all things you want to highlight.
And that's going to look different for every student.
So thinking about the involvement you have in the community, whether it's community organizations,
sports organizations, what are some things you can bring to the table in your post-secondary
portfolio that are really going to show who you are and what you can bring to an organization?
A couple other things to consider just before we pass it off to Miss Fenn to talk about
the post-secondary process.
Mountain is an incredible school with a plethora of opportunities for kids to get involved
in.
We just had Clubs Day a couple of weeks ago, great turnout.
There's over 40 or 45 clubs that are up and running already this school year.
Councils, we have lots of students involved with grade councils, leadership, all sorts
of different things.
Work teams, this year we're running almost 50 school teams ranging from grade 8 through
grade 12.
Scholarships, advanced placement, work experience volunteer, we'll talk about those things later
on.
But really, in short, we want students to embrace all aspects of what Mountain has to
offer.
As I say, we're very fortunate to work and learn in a fantastic school.
People volunteer to create lots of opportunities for students.
We try to match students up or encourage them to pursue some of those things, but a lot
of that comes down to kids identifying where is it that I want to be, how do I get involved,
and really taking the time to embrace all aspects of school life at Mountain.
We'll loop back to a few of those things later on.
Just before I pass it over to Miss Fenn, we are going to monitor, there's a group of us
here in the room together, we're going to do our best to monitor the chat as people
are presenting.
We'll try to answer questions in real time.
Obviously, there's too many people for everybody to jump in and ask questions or raise your
hand in the meeting.
So we're going to monitor the chat so you can ask your questions there.
Each presenter will follow up when they're done presenting, they'll loop back through
the chat and just respond to anything specific that wasn't addressed.
So feel free to share your questions as we go.
All right, and with no further ado, I'm going to introduce you to Jackie Fenn.
Jackie's our new counselor, head of student services, our counseling department head,
joined us from Burnaby South, tons of experience.
We're thrilled to have her here.
And she's going to walk you through a little bit about the graduation and post-secondary
pathways.
So, Miss Fenn, over to you.
Thank you so much.
So hi, everyone.
My name is Miss Fenn, as Miss Ronzi had mentioned.
So for graduation requirements,
Students need a minimum of 80 credits towards their graduation, which can, it's a combination
of curricular courses that are required as well as elective courses.
It's just lagging a little bit.
So we'll just hold on there.
So for the graduation requirements, students look at the graduation requirements that start
in grade 10.
Grade 8 and 9 courses are the courses that help build onto the courses for grade 10.
So to graduate with 80 credits, students need to have 12 required courses.
You need English 10, 11, 12.
You need socials 10, 11, or 12.
Science 10, 11.
Math 10, 11.
Physical and health education 10.
Career life education.
And then you need to have one course in either fine arts or applied skill between grade
10, 11, and 12, as well as seven elective courses that can be either from courses taking
in school or courses taken from external credits.
And in that, you have to have four courses that are at the grade 12 level.
Students then also need to take one Indigenous-focused class.
This can be either fulfilled by students taking English First Peoples 10, 11, or 12, as well
or taking BC First Peoples 12.
These also take Career Life Connections, also known as CLC 11 and 12.
Then in grade 10, students will end up writing two assessments.
So you write a graduation literacy 10 assessment and a graduation numeracy 10 assessment.
So for those of you that are currently in grade 10, you'll be writing that in January
during the semester turnaround.
And then grade 12, you end up writing a graduation literacy 12 assessment, and grade 12 will
write that in November.
If you're currently in grade 12 and you didn't write the 10 and numeracy and the 10 literacy,
you'll write that in January.
Students can also, any student can actually get credits for external credits.
So that can be for external activities that you're involved in outside of school.
This can be something like a language challenge exam.
So an email went out a few weeks back that there's language challenge exams that the
Delta School District offers that offers to all the districts to write.
And there are specific second languages that are many home languages.
Students who might be in certain levels of music or dance.
So for example, if you play piano in grade six, seven or eight, you can get external credits
for some youth leadership.
If you're on a provincial sports team or a BC Summer Games or a national team, you might
qualify for external credits.
We always let students know to come and see us in counseling to let us know because there's
so many different types of credits that are out there that can be put on your transcript.
There are three different types of post second, three main types of post secondary options
that we always let families know.
So the first being that there's universities.
So universities actually kind of go into three different types of universities.
There's a traditional research university.
So that's your research intensive.
That's what you're thinking of your UBC, your SFU, your UNBC, University of Toronto, McGill.
Those are no, those have professional programs, undergraduate degrees, graduate degrees.
Then there's what's called teaching intensive universities.
These are where you see like Capilano University, Portland Polytechnic University, Thompson
Rivers University, the Fraser Valley.
This is these offer.
They offer some certificates, some diplomas, some undergraduate and graduate degrees, but
they also offer amazing opportunities for students to go to either do university transfer
or offer upgrading opportunities or specialty programs.
And then there's known as the specialty universities.
These are those niche program universities that offer bachelor's degrees and master's
degrees for specific programs.
So these are when you're thinking of the Emily Carr or University of Art, the, you know,
M.F.C.R. University of Art Design or Royal Roads University.
Then there's colleges.
So colleges encompass the same as universities in their courses, their credits and their
credentials.
That means that university professors have to have the same credentials when you're teaching
at college and in university.
They differ in the university in sense of class size.
So they're smaller than university cost.
You're about 60% of university and admissions.
Some colleges do offer bachelor's degrees.
They offer certificates, diplomas, trades, upgrading opportunities and university transfer.
So this is like your Douglas, your Langara, your BCC.
And then the last is institutions.
And this focus more on the technical and trades.
So we're looking at BCIT, Justice Institute at BC, Nicola Valley.
They do offer some bachelor's degrees, some certificates, some diplomas and master's degrees.
So those are like the three different types of encompasses in post-secondary.
So for university applications.
So when students apply to most universities across Canada, students actually choose two
different faculties to apply to because you choose your first choice and then you choose
your backup.
So for example, as a student who might be applying to faculty of applied sciences, so
engineering, that might be their first choice with the backup of science.
Or students that might be applying for faculty of sciences or first choice, they might have
faculty of arts as their second.
It's really important though, and the universities let us know this, to not choose the same faculty
is both your first and your second choice.
Because if you're not accepted to the faculty, their first choice, they're not going to,
it's not going to be a better chance to get into it for a second choice.
Unfortunately, there are students that do choose both of them, first and second choice.
It's also really important than the universities have let us know it's really important that
students meet all the prerequisite admission requirements for both the first and second
choice.
And the other thing is that faculties that are highly competitive.
It's important that you have that as your first choice.
So for example, if you're if you are really interested in faculty of engineering, faculty
of applied sciences for engineering, or faculty of business, it's really important to have
that as your first choice.
Because if it's your second, those two faculties are so in demand that if it's your second,
they won't look at that because they were already looking at the first choice.
BC college is so most colleges are accepted on a first come first serve basis.
So we recommend for students to apply online as soon as possible to secure their spot.
Many colleges open their applications October 1.
So for the grade 12 currently, they're already open.
Some program college program acceptance is based on just basic graduation, where some
do have course requirements.
So for example, you may need a minimum mark in English 12, or English 12 first peoples.
And the other great thing is that college also offers upgrading opportunities.
So some colleges do offer some grade 12 courses maybe you weren't able to take in high school.
Now college university transfer, we know that there's some myths out there about college
university.
So what that means is university transfer means you start studying at college, and then
you transfer to university to complete your studies.
So university recognizes the education that you took at college.
So for example, if you did two years at college, and then you did two years at university,
you gobble up your all your credits, you get your bachelor's degree.
Nowhere on that transcript on that graduate certificate from UBC, SFU, UVic, U of T nowhere
does it say that you got a faculty of science PSU at Douglas Hirsch.
Nowhere does it say that.
The great advantages of college is it's lower cost for your degree, smaller class sizes,
and universities actually really like transfer students from college.
The challenges is it does require more planning from you because you need to make sure that
your courses will actually transfer to the University of Choice.
But to help you in that there's something called the BC Transfer Guide, and the link
will be on the presentation as well.
And that's an amazing opportunity for you to be able to see which courses from every
college in BC will transfer to the university.
So there are some admission updates for UBC.
So UBC, for example, has changed over the years how they're evaluating applications.
What they've let us know is no matter what faculty you're applying to, they're going
to broadly evaluate your academic history by looking at all of your grade 11 and your
grade 12 courses.
They do recommend that applicants have a minimum of six academic courses.
They say they're also going to look at individual grades and key courses.
So that means you have to have strong grades in those courses like your English, English
for Peoples or, for example, Pre-Calculus 12 if you're applying for business or sciences.
Each faculty does have degree specific requirements.
It's important that students check the UBC website because that does change every so
often.
UBC also has let us know they're looking closely at courses that you choose to take in high
school.
So they want to look at did you pursue all your academic interests by taking a range
of different subjects?
Did you challenge yourself by taking academic courses or advanced courses or first year
university?
And did you demonstrate knowledge in your chosen area of study by taking courses related
to the degree that you want to apply for?
And then UBC has what's called the personal profile.
Now brand new, brand new, brand new this year that UBC let us know is that they now are
going to be offering first review offers.
So what that means is UBC is no longer going to use the first round offer.
So they used to have a December 1st admission deadline.
That is no longer admission deadline.
So now students now open now in October.
So students can submit their applications right now for them to be eligible for first
review offers.
So that means that students applications will now be reviewed as soon as you submit your
application and when UBC has all their required information.
So what you need to do is you need to submit what's called a student transcript service,
which is your marks get sent to UBC.
They have let us know that due to competitive and limited space at UBC that not all students
are going to receive their first review offer.
So they're going to review again.
So they'll look between March and April.
They say that UBC typically offers admission only to the strongest applicants during this
first portion, but they don't fill up all the spaces.
So you don't need to worry about them filling all the spaces.
They do have spaces for regular admission.
And then UBC has what's called the personal profile.
So this is a way that is really important for UBC.
It's a part and part of their application process.
So they're going to review again.
That is really important for UBC.
It's a part and part of their application.
It helps.
It's a way for you to kind of tell UBC if you're prepared for university.
And it also allows you to see if they're going to give you an entrance scholarship.
So it gives you a chance to tell UBC what's important to you.
So there's different questions that you're going to answer.
And basically what they want to see is what are your significant achievements?
What have you learned through your experience?
What challenges have you overcome in your life?
So there's different types of questions.
Some are 50 words.
Some are up to 200 words.
What they've let us know is for you to take time to reflect.
Don't just list your activities and experiences, but explain what you've actually learned from
them.
Be specific.
So use details, provide context, elaborate on your answers, and be true to who you are.
So don't focus on what you think UBC wants to hear.
The important thing is to use your own unique voice.
A sample question that they've done in the past is explain how you responded to a significant
challenge that you've encountered and what did you learn from the process.
So they want to see what you've done and what you've learned and how can you express that.
Now with SFU, SFU has also changed how they're evaluating your application.
They also said all approved courses matter, meaning grade 11 and 12 courses are going
to be used in the evaluation.
They say that we are comprehensively evaluating your high school transcript.
So applicants need to present a minimum of five approved grade 12 courses.
So your English 12 plus four more.
And students need to receive a minimum of 70% final grade in English 11 or 12.
And then each faculty has their own approved list of courses.
It's important that you go to the SFU website because everything is listed there.
Now they've also changed for their early admission.
So SFU has now to have early admission is based on strong academic performance in all
approved grade grade 11 courses, as well as any grade 12 courses that you have at the
time evaluation.
So basically for current grade 12s, anything that you've completed up to after summer
school, any final grades that you have up to there, that's what they're going to be
looking at for early admission.
Offers of admission at this stage are limited and typically extended to students with high
academic standing.
They haven't really let us know how many students they'll be allowing for admission.
But they did say that their students are going to find out about their decisions between
November and January.
So there are going to be some students that are going to find out their admissions during
the next few months.
They said to be considered for early admission, then applicants must present their application
as early as possible.
So prior to the end of January.
So it's important to start really working on those applications now to have your best
foot forward.
Other universities in BC.
So for example, University of Victoria, they have an admission deadline of January 31st.
They've actually given an email for us if students have any specific admission questions
to contact an admission recruitment officer.
So it's recruitment at uvic.ca.
And Capilano is just in North Van, just top over the bridge.
And they have some programs that can be quite competitive.
So they recommend to apply as soon as possible.
But they have other just general programs as well.
The important thing is to check the Capilano website for specific admission.
They did say that undergraduate admission requirements can vary by program.
But usually, at most for Capilano programs, the school has the minimum completion of an
So 60% in English 12 or English 12 First Peoples plus two academic grade 12 courses.
Trains program.
So the Burnaby School District has some amazing trains program that you're going to hear a
little bit about for students that can apply online while students are actually apply while
you're actually here.
So students can actually apply for it going into grade 11 or 12.
And they're they're fantastic.
I'm Miss Manning and Miss G and the career center.
We'll talk more about that.
BCAT is an amazing school that has many different types of programs that fall from trades that
are certificate diploma and bachelor's degrees.
Some admission can be competitive.
So you may need to have, you know, an arrange either from English 50% to 85 depending on
the program.
And they do offer a virtual information sessions.
I always recommend families to go on to BCAT website.
They have information sessions that you can go on virtually.
You can find out all of the information about the programs.
There's also work BC and skill trade.
BC are both great resources to learn about different trades or apprenticeships or pathways.
And there's some links that you can go directly to that information.
So how do students apply to their post-secondary schools?
So for students in grade 12 to when you're applying to the majority of the BC colleges
or university, you do it through what's called education planner BC where students will have
for an online account, complete an educational profile, choose what colleges or universities
you want to apply to, choose what specific program you want to apply to.
So are you applying to business or arts or sciences?
Provide additional any kind of specific information that that institution is looking for and then
pay your fee.
That's the key is you got to pay your fee.
Now it's important that if you are applying for schools outside of BC, some schools have
their own other programs.
So like Ontario has their own what's called OAC.
So you have to go through their portal and then other universities across Canada have
different types.
Now there are some possible entrance post-secondary exams that students may have to write.
So for students are looking at going into the United States, you are some schools do
require SATs, some schools are optional.
But for SATs for students that are interested, it is recommended that you have it written
by the spring of grade 11.
The reason why I'm saying the spring of grade 11 is because you have to have all of your
results to be able to apply by December 31.
So by writing it in the spring of grade 11, that does give you an opportunity to rewrite
it before that deadline comes out.
TOEFL might be one that students have to write and that's for BC universities.
Generally for students with four years of instruction or under four years of instruction
in English, other provinces could be five, but you have to double check.
IELTS is international students.
So there are some interesting ideas for universities that generally for students with less than
three to four years of instruction in English.
But there are some universities that might have their own admission entrance tests, but
they'll let you know that when you apply.
Now there are some upcoming post-secondary presentations that are happening here at Mountain.
So October 27th, if you're interested, BC School of Business and Media is going to be
here.
So the SFO Victoria is coming on October 29th.
SFU Beattie School of Business is November 5th.
November 14th is SFU Faculty of Applied Science, so Engineering and Computer Science.
November 27th is Faculty of Health Science.
The both BC post-secondary mini-fair, which is fantastic.
It's a mini-fair happening December 3rd in the Upper Commons where a lot of colleges
and universities across BC will be here that you can actually talk to advisors.
And then December 5th is a UBC Sauter School of Business.
Now where to find more information about post-secondary institutions?
Well post-secondary websites for general information or for virtual tours are really important.
We have view books and student services for some post-secondary.
There's also the BC post-secondary website that you can go to.
There's presentations that I mentioned at Mountain here with various schools that are
advertised.
You can look in the school bulletin.
The Career Centre does a weekly news bulletin that they post in your CLC 12 teams for grade
12s.
In the Career Centre they also have paper copies.
And if you haven't already, sign up for the Birdie Mountain Secondary Counseling Instagram
page.
We post information on there as well.
Now who can you contact about graduation and other course stuff or anything else?
So here at Mountain we have four counselors.
We have Ms. Erin that goes with students with last names A to G-O.
Ms. D-C, student last names G-R to M-A.
I'm last names M-C to T-H and Mr. Hoyle is last names from T-I to Z.
So you can contact us about anything from graduation course or anything in between personal
friends, everything.
But thank you everyone.
Hi there.
My name is Tammy Bellier.
I am the scholarship coordinator for Birdie Mountain Secondary.
So I'm just going to talk to you for a few minutes about some scholarship opportunities.
Scholarships are monetary awards designed to support students' education.
They're not just about grades.
Students can receive scholarships for academic achievement, demonstrate financial need, community
service, leadership, and other unique talents and interests.
Scholarships can come from many places, our school and district, the government, post-secondary,
and private organizations.
The point is there's many opportunities out there, but each one has its own requirements.
Every scholarship has its own criteria.
So most common criteria include strong academic performance, demonstrated financial need,
excellence in areas like music, drama, athletics, or trades, and involvement in community service.
But what's important to note is that more and more scholarships are looking for well-rounded
students, those who show good balance between academics, extracurricular, and personal life.
When you're in grade 12, you'll be added to a scholarship team.
This is the main hub where all scholarship information and application and instructions
will be posted.
You'll find scholarships from the school, district, government, and private organizations
there.
For post-secondary scholarships, you're going to want to go directly to the university or
scholarship websites and apply through their financial assistance sites.
In the meantime, websites like ScholarTree.ca and YConnick.com are excellent tools.
They're both Canadian websites, and they offer free scholarship matching and give access
to a database of over 30,000 opportunities.
So what is needed to apply?
One of the first steps for the process is completing a scholarship profile form.
There's a picture of it on this slide.
This form is required to be considered for all of the school and the district awards,
so that should be completed by all grade 12s.
Many scholarships will ask for certain documents, so it's good to prepare those ahead of time.
Transcripts, which can be downloaded from the ministry website with instructions on
how to do that on the scholarship team as well.
A resume and community service list.
Now this is something grade 10s and 11s should be building right now.
You want to keep those organized and up to date with contacts and number of hours that
participate in all of these different activities.
And reference letters.
So teachers will need at least two weeks notice to give a reference letter.
And on the scholarship team, there's a reference letter request form that basically you fill
out and it gives the teachers information about some of the activities that you participated
in as well as what award that they're filling out the form for.
So they can tailor the letter to that form.
You don't need to collect the letters far in advance.
So teachers are stronger when they're recent and specific to the award.
Finally, deadlines.
Due dates vary widely, but one thing is always true.
The deadlines are firm.
Late applications are not considered.
And that's why grade 12s should make a habit to check the scholarship team regularly so
that they don't miss any opportunities.
Thank you.
Hello, my name is Jen Riley.
I am the Advanced Placement Coordinator here at Mountain.
I've got my email address on the screen there and my room number as well.
So you can contact me anytime if you have any questions about AP.
So I'll just spend a few minutes tonight talking about what AP is, why you should consider
taking AP, some questions that I get asked a lot, and then just more specific information
about what we offer here at Mountain.
First, what is AP?
So AP classes are university or college level classes that students are taking while they're
still in high school.
But there is a standardized exam that they can take as well in May.
And if they do well enough on that exam, they actually get university or college credit
for that course as well.
Yeah, so let's get into why you'd want to take an AP class.
Lots of reasons, but I think the most important is you're developing really strong university
level skills to get you ready for that next level of learning.
We all know that the transition between high school and university can be pretty challenging.
And so AP classes are really going to help prepare students.
And in Richmond as well, so students are studying topics that maybe they're really passionate
about.
They might discover a new career interest or academic pathway they didn't know about
before.
And the research kind of backs all of this up.
If you look at studies done in Canada, students going to UBC or University of Alberta, the
College Board looked at students who took AP courses and compared how they were doing
to those who did not take AP classes.
And the students who took AP classes in high school are doing a lot better in terms of
GPA, their graduate unit higher rates, they are staying in their programs longer.
So yeah, the research backs it up and the universities are aware of this research.
They know that AP classes are going to prepare students and so they're looking for that to
be on students' transcripts.
So yeah, that's kind of speaks to my third point there, which is that it helps you stand
out when you're applying.
It shows universities that you're ready to challenge yourself academically, that you're
too ready to move to the next level.
And then the last reason to take an AP class is it can potentially save you a lot of time
and money once you begin attending university because I mentioned earlier, if you do well
enough on the exam, you can potentially get credit for that course.
And so if students choose to use that credit, they'd be saving a lot of money and also time.
Okay, so here are some questions I get asked a lot about AP.
One of the main questions is, does my AP exam, how does the AP exam score work?
Like, is that related to my class grade in any way?
And the answer to that is no.
So the AP exam score is separate from the course grade.
So the grade you get in class is given to you from your teacher that goes on your high
school transcript.
And then your AP exam score is sent to your university once you begin attending that university
and you can then use that for your university credit.
Can students just take one AP class?
Yeah, I think that's one of the main advantages of AP compared to some other programs like
IB, if you're familiar with that.
It's not a program where you have to take every course at an AP level.
You can take one, you can take two, it's very flexible.
So you can take, you know, many or just one.
Do all Canadian universities accept AP?
Yes.
So what I would recommend if you know what university you plan on attending is just do
a quick search.
If you search UBC, for example, and then advanced placement, each university will have a page
explaining how they transfer the credits over, which courses match up with which AP classes
at that school and how they convert different exam scores to different percentages at that
particular university.
So that would be a really good search to do once you've got your university nailed down.
This is probably the most popular question I get asked by email.
I usually answer a few of these every week.
Can I take an AP exam without taking the class at Burnaby Mountain?
A lot of students are very keen and they want to take a lot of classes and they don't always
fit in their schedule, which is great.
And you can self study for AP and just take the exam, but you can't do that at a Burnaby
school.
We're just not set up as an exam testing center.
We only have space and resources for students who are taking the class at our school, but
there are places around the lower mainland where you can take an exam.
And so just do some research and find one of those and sign up.
I think if you're planning to do that this year, the deadline is approaching pretty quick.
So you'd want to get on that now if you haven't already.
I see some people are answering, asking some questions.
I'll just address them at the end if I don't hit those in my slides here.
Do students have to write the AP exam?
No, but it's strongly encouraged.
I think the experience is really valuable.
And the research also shows that students who write the exam are getting more prepared
for university as well.
And then how many AP classes should I take?
I think this obviously varies for each student, but what the research said is like two to
three is a good number.
Students who take multiple AP classes are doing better in university than those who
take just one.
That kind of makes sense because you're gaining different experience, different skills with
different subject areas.
But after kind of three, the advantage of taking more classes kind of plateaus.
So if you compare someone who took three classes to those who took eight, nine, ten, they're
not doing significantly better on average.
Yeah, and I think spreading them out, I think is a good idea too.
And that's kind of what I'll get into now.
So these are all the AP classes that we typically offer here at Burnaby Mountain.
Students are really lucky to be at this school if they're interested in AP because we've
got a great program.
Burnaby is kind of known across Canada really as one of the main, one of the best, having
one of the best AP programs.
And our school is no exception.
So we've got lots to offer in lots of different subject areas.
I'll just mention a few things on this slide here.
So one thing to keep in mind is most of these courses we offer consistently every year because
we have a good amount of students who register.
But there's a few courses which we kind of offer every second year or so depending on
interests.
So music theory would be one of those.
The last few years we've been offering that once every two years.
Same with macroeconomics and microeconomics.
We are running that this year, but in the past that's kind of depended year to year
on how many students select it.
The sciences, keep in mind that those are all two-year programs at Mountain.
So for biology and chemistry, students would be taking biology and leaven enriched or chemistry
and leaven enriched usually in their grade 11 year.
And then in the grade 12 year, they would take AP biology and AP chemistry.
So it's a two-year program, but just one exam at the end in there when they're taking the
AP class.
Physics is a little bit different.
It is a two-year program as well, but you're taking two exams with that.
So typically students would take physics one in grade 11.
They would write the exam for physics one, and then it takes two exams.
And a lot of universities require them to take both physics exams and get a certain
score on both in order to get the credit.
Yeah, and then I'll just give you some advice maybe or just some next steps if you're thinking
about AP and you have some questions.
Deciding what AP courses to take, I think take things that you're interested in taking,
things that you wouldn't mind spending time studying and then things related to the degree
you might want to take.
I think what's really important is you go and talk to the AP teachers who teach those
classes.
They know a lot about that subject area.
A lot of them have been teaching those courses for a long time and are kind of experts in
that field.
So talk to those teachers, talk to your counselors.
I can help too if you want kind of a bigger perspective and to help plan.
And a lot of AP classes you can take as early as grade 11 and sometimes even grade 10.
So trying to spread out if you want to take multiple over some years because you don't
want to take, you know, four or five in grade 12 and have all of those exams at the same
time.
That's a lot to handle.
So spreading them out if you can, I think is a really good idea.
And then just for applying for AP, you would just select those AP courses you want to take
during course selection, which happens in February.
Yeah, and so I'll just address here questions that people have been asking.
So one person asked, do colleges accept APs?
Yes, but if you want to, oh, someone answered that already.
Yeah, so just I would just Google the name of the college and then advanced placement
and you'll find information about what they do.
If a student takes AP test and the score is low, can we not submit to the university?
Yeah, so the university, you don't have to send any of your scores.
That's completely up to you.
So many students just write the test and then they never submit their score and they just
choose to retake the course again once they're at university.
And that's totally fine.
That's kind of the nice thing about the exam scores is you can keep them private if you
want to.
Although I did hear that there's a few top universities in the United States, some Ivy
League schools that are now requesting all of the exam grades, but I think that's only
a few schools.
So that won't apply to many people here, I don't think.
Do universities in the United States accept AP courses?
Yeah. So pretty much all around the world, all major universities are going to be
accepting AP classes.
So these classes are taken all around the world.
Most major universities will accept them.
But I think just to be sure, I would check the university website to ensure how they're
exactly translated.
AP classes are considered electives.
OK, this is a good question.
Depends, depends.
So I'm going to use two examples.
Can you go back to this slide?
Yeah. OK. So this is a list of our courses.
Let's say an AP class lines up with a grade 12 level class.
Like I'm going to use English Literature and Composition as my example.
So that class matches pretty well with English 12, which is a graduation requirement.
We're not going to make students take English 12 and English Literature and Composition
AP. They would take either or.
So actually, for those types of courses that match up with the grade 12 class, students
are getting dual credit.
So that means they're getting credit for the AP class on their transcript and also
English 12.
So in that case, it's not really an elective.
You're just taking the AP version of that grade 12 class.
And then similarly for biology, chemistry, physics, all of those classes align pretty
well with the grade 12 version.
So they would get the dual credit.
Things like AP Computer Science, that's more of an elective course.
That's not going to be a graduation requirement.
So they would just that would be treated more like an elective.
I hope that answers the question.
Did I answer that well enough, counselor?
OK. And do I need to get good marks in related courses and then I can be enrolled in AP
class? The easy answer to that is I think if you show interest in the class and there's
space in the class, you can take AP.
But you should be aiming to prepare yourself for some hard work in an AP class.
Like it is a university level class.
So you want to be doing the things you need to do to prepare yourself for that.
So if you're yeah, I think it's a good idea in the courses leading up to that class to
be striving for good marks, because then you're going to be prepared to take on that hard
work. How do we know if they are?
Wait, do I need how do we know if they are equivalent?
Oh, yeah. You can ask me or the counselor or a teacher.
I don't. Yeah, I don't know if I have time here to go through all 16, but you can send me
an email or counselor an email or the student can drop by my class and we can go over which
ones match up with which courses.
Is it mandatory to take AP courses?
No, but I would highly recommend it if you're considering a academic university program
after high school. I think taking at least one, if not two AP courses is a really, really
good idea to prepare yourself.
What is the AP selection process?
I think it varies for each class, but generally if there's space and the student has the
prerequisites for that class, they can take it.
Yeah. So obviously for something like English Literature and Composition, the prerequisite
would be like English 11.
They'll have to finish that first.
We're not going to put a grade nine student in an AP English literature class.
So there's certain classes, you know, you need to take certain things beforehand to get
in. Yeah, and that would be isn't there fees for the exam?
Yes, there are fees for the exam.
The fee this year is one hundred and fifty dollars.
Most of that fee just gets sent straight to the college board.
It's there's a fee that we pay to essentially create the exam and mark it.
And then we need a little bit of to cover the costs for a proctor and things like that.
So the fee, one hundred and fifty dollars per exam.
But when you compare that to what a course would cost, the difference is quite a bit.
And a lot of these courses actually like biology, chemistry, psychology.
Those are the ones that come to mind immediately.
Those are all covering two university classes.
So students get, I think, eight credit university credits for biology for just taking that
one one exam, which is a pretty big advantage.
How many AP classes do I need to take for U of T?
I think what I said, yeah, it just depends on the student, what program you're applying for.
Like, I think I would. Yeah, OK.
Yeah. Yeah. Do universities look more favorably to students with AP during entrance assessments?
Yeah, they do. I went to a AP event and the UBC admissions officer was there.
And he said, yeah, we look favorably on applications that have AP for some of those reasons
As I mentioned earlier, you're going to look more prepared.
You're going to show that you're ready to take on the challenge of post-secondary.
So I think, you know, an A in AP looks a lot better than an A in a regular class.
And even a slightly lower mark in AP, I think, would be looking a lot better than a slightly higher mark in a regular class.
Yeah. Yes, the course is free of charge.
You just need to pay the exam fee. That's correct.
Yes. Would it be helpful to take an enriched course to be selected?
Yeah, I think an enriched course really helps to prepare students for the academic rigor of AP for sure.
So I think leading up to taking AP, if you're interested in that, do all of the things that, you know, would help you prepare.
So taking enriched classes, getting good grades, going for help, you know, taking classes that are related to that subject area, I think would all be good, good things.
Well, lots of questions. I love it.
How many AP credits do I need to have for the requirements?
Not sure what that's asking.
Oh, for U of T. I don't know.
Yeah. Okay.
Are self-studied AP exams useful?
That not real, not so much.
So someone asked if self-studied AP exams are useful.
So AP exam scores do not show up on transcripts from high school.
So the only way that that would be useful is if you wrote it into like a statement you were writing on your application or if you put it on some kind of academic resume that you had gotten so many exams and what scores you've gotten.
But really those self-studied AP exams are only going to be useful once you start attending that university.
You'll get credit for those courses, but you won't be able to use them for your high school GPA.
Oh, my gosh. Okay.
Yeah, maybe I'll just continue answering in the chat while the next person goes.
That might be a better idea.
Yeah, thanks.
Okay.
Thanks, everyone.
Yeah.
I think we can talk.
Hi, everybody.
There we go.
Hi.
I'm Ms. G.
This is Ms. Manning and we work at the Career Center just across from the main office.
Those are lovely photos.
So we in our school, we have courses, career courses that are offered from grade 10 through to grade 12.
The Career Life Education 10 course is taught typically in a classroom here.
And so I know some students who take it online.
It is a required course for graduation.
It's a four credit course.
And then Ms. Manning and I teach the Career Life Connections 11 and 12 courses.
Those courses are taught outside the timetable and they're also required for graduation.
And then we also coordinate the work experience component as well for senior students.
So we'll get into that in the next few slides.
So the Career Life Education, so those courses we were talking about, the grade 10 course, as mentioned, is mandatory for graduation.
Students take that as one of their eight classes that they take.
The CLC 11 and 12, the Career Life Connections 11 and 12 courses, we meet a couple of times during the year.
In fact, we met with all the grade 12s last Friday and we're meeting with all the grade 11s this Friday.
That content is delivered through meetings and assignments through teams.
The culmination of the career courses is the capstone presentation, which students do in April of their grade 12 year.
And that capstone presentation is really just a presentation of their learning journey from grade 10 through to grade 12,
including also what their next steps are after they leave high school.
So really, that's the purpose of the career programs is to get them ready for and make a plan for what are they going to do when they leave here?
What are those next steps look like?
Yeah, our role is to complement what's happening in the classroom here at the school by providing students with opportunities to get involved in the community
and help build their portfolio and get ready for next steps, whether that be going to work or going to post-secondary right after high school.
Part of that is that students need to do some work experience to graduate.
And this is community work experience.
So it could be paid, could be volunteer, a combination of.
Minimum requirement to graduate is 30 hours.
But most of our students here take an elective in grade 12 called Work Experience 12A, which includes 80 hours of work experience.
And then students do that on weekends after school, on breaks, especially like summer break is a big time when students get out because they have lots of time to build and build their resume and work.
There's lots of great reasons why doing work experience is important.
Again, supporting what students are doing in the classroom.
We want to get them out exploring different careers, figure out what they like, what they don't like, help them build some skills, build their resumes
so that when they apply for scholarships or when they go to job interviews, they have experiences they can draw upon.
A lot of our students end up getting part time work, too, from the different experiences that they do in the community,
the networking that they that they build, they they meet mentors, they get advice and connect with adults and other peers in the community.
And that's how they learn about different programs and different opportunities that are available to them.
And then they make references from professional contacts and they'll help them when they apply to university and also when they present their capstone in grade 12.
So if you're wondering what work experience opportunities are available, the students are all in teams.
Work experience is completed in grade 11 and grade 12.
So for the graduation requirement, students do need to be in grade 11 and grade 12.
Students can, of course, be volunteering in grade 8, 9 and 10.
But the program that we have here at the school supports students through their grade 11 and grade 12 year to get involved in the community.
And it's only during those two years that they can complete the 30 hours needed for graduation.
We'll talk a little bit about other things that students can do.
There's a service award they can get for volunteering in earlier grades.
But in their senior years, which is what we're focusing on here, students do need to complete a minimum of 30 hours.
They may have their own contacts.
Students often come to us and say, I have a part time job.
Can I count that for 30 hours?
Absolutely.
I volunteer with my community group, my soccer club, my faith organization.
Could I use that towards my hours?
For sure.
We have paperwork that we provide the students with, so that counts.
Most of our students here at Burme Mountain go on to complete an additional 50 hours of volunteering in the community for all the reasons we just stated.
It's super beneficial for them and for their growth and really does give them things to write about as they were talking about those post-secondary applications.
It really gives them experiences to draw on.
So the students are all in teams where they can see all the different work experience opportunities.
If I can just go back to the last slide real quick.
Sorry, Mr.
Honsley.
If you would like to know what kind of work experience opportunities are available to your student, if you go to the Burme Mountain website, you can see that the student bulletin is in the quick link circled there in the red at the side.
We post weekly different work experience opportunities that are available to students.
We also post a section on what we call career exploration and leadership development.
So these might be workshops that students can attend in the community.
Sometimes they're held at the local post-secondary institutions.
And then we also have a whole section on post-secondary information sessions, both once here at Mountain, but also a lot of online and Zoom sessions are held now for different post-secondary institutions and even things you can go to in person.
All of that information is posted in our school bulletin and students can access it in their teams as well.
So currently, these are just some different experiences that we thought we would highlight while we had an audience this evening.
Locally, Charles Rommel Centre is by Seaforth Elementary, and they're currently looking for some volunteers to help out on the Pro-D Day, and they have some winter break camps.
So that opportunity, for example, would be open to our current grade 11 and grade 12 students.
And then at our school, we're actually hosting a volleyball tournament next week, and they're looking for volunteers to help run the concession.
Something like that is open to anybody in grade 8 to grade 12, because it's in-house, it's in the school, it runs after school.
So if anybody wants to volunteer in any grade, they can come.
We've got a sign up sheet in the Career Centre.
Also right now, the Temporary Cameron at Lougheed Mall has a Halloween event they're looking for volunteers on Saturday, October 25th in the afternoon.
There's a youth centre, Creekside Youth Centre, next to Stoney Creek Community School, runs programs for elementary school students after school on Mondays and Wednesdays.
They're looking for volunteers.
Locally, we're connected with Code Ninjas.
They run learning to code camps for kids, and they're running an orientation on October 30th for anybody in grade 11 and grade 12 that wants to
volunteer there for their after school or Saturday programs.
We're also hosting a big conference here at our school for all the education assistants in the district.
And so we need some volunteers for that event.
It's in the morning of October 24th on the ProD.
Any grade, anybody grade 8 to grade 12 can help out.
We've got to sign up in the Career Centre.
And then there's a few other things to highlight that are in and posted in the bulletin, but we have lots of local thrift stores that need volunteers.
Grouse Mountain and Mount Seymour have just opened up their ski and snowboard schools, have a volunteer program where youth can get involved and they get free pass too, which is pretty exciting to the Hill.
Their PEAK program runs after school and we need peer tutors.
So if you're in grade 10, 11, 12 and you want to help out some grade 8s or 9s after school, come and come see us.
We can tell you more about that.
There's the local YMCA Betty Aller.
They're looking for students to help out for their programs after school on a weekend.
There's an artist apprenticeship project through Burnaby Art Gallery.
And then another event we wanted to highlight is a program like UBC's Chemical and Biological Engineering.
They actually hold host events for just high school students where you can go become a high school student for the day and tour their labs and see what the classrooms are like.
So opportunities like this are posted on the bulletin that Miss Manning mentioned.
So go and check it out.
What's in the school bulletin and there's new stuff every week.
So it's important that, you know, as students are looking for things that they find things that really speak to them and apply to them.
So as we were mentioning, students in grade 8s to 12 can accumulate service hours, either volunteering in the school or in the community.
Students in grade 8, 9 and 10 can apply those hours towards a service award.
The award is given in grade 10 at our end of year ceremony.
Students just need to grab a form from the Career Center and we can help them with that and they can just write down any of the volunteering that they've done through grade 8, 9 and 10.
They have a minimum of 50 hours to get a minor award and 100 hours gets them a major.
That form is due on April 30th.
So it doesn't follow the exact school year because we need time, of course, to process that and have that ready for the award ceremony at the end of the year.
Senior students can also get an award.
And most of our senior students, I think, know the drill on that one because we talked to them about it a lot.
But they can also get a service award for any hours that are done either in the school or in the community above the hours they've used for their work experience graduation requirement.
This is just another graphic that we put together just to explain the exact same thing.
Everyone does 30 hours.
Most Burnery Mountain students complete an additional 50 hours.
That additional 50 does have to be volunteer.
It can't be paid.
And then for senior students, grade 11 and 12, any hours above that can go towards a service award.
We have many students who not only get credit for the work experience course, but also get major service awards.
There's so many great opportunities for students to get involved both in the school and in the community that for students who are keen, the opportunities there.
And we really make use of the breaks, winter break, summer break, spring break, with lots of opportunities for students to get involved and really build that portfolio and figure out who they are and what they want to do in the world.
OK, so another thing that we organize and coordinate here in the school is the application process for the district industry training programs.
These are programs that are open to students in grades 11 and 12.
They're also available, some of them in a sixth year format.
So if a grade 12 student this year said, well, I wish I could have taken the carpentry program, for example, or the electrician program here at our school, then they can still apply and take those programs in a sixth year.
So we have different categories. We have what's called the youth training trades programs.
These are all trades hands on programs.
Some of them are at a Burnaby High School and some of them are hosted actually at a post secondary institution like Vancouver Community College or BCIT.
And then we have what's called portfolio development programs, Industry Connect.
These are all programs that help students develop a portfolio to get ready for post secondary.
And then we have industry certification programs. Students get a certificate and then sometimes even credit a post secondary for some of the courses that they take in these in these programs.
So every year we have a district evening where you can your parents in the community and students and families can come out and meet the instructors of these programs, ask questions, meet some students who are currently in the program.
So it's at Burnaby Central and this year it's going to be on January 14th and we'll send it to the evening.
We'll send out some more information through the listserv closer to that date.
And then this is a great opportunity to come out, like I said, meet some of the teachers and ask questions and find out more about some of these programs that students can take in grade 11 and grade 12 or grade 12.
And certainly students and families, if you have questions about any of the programs, please reach out to us.
We've been doing this for a long time and we're really familiar with those programs and they really are fantastic for the right students.
And applications for those programs will come out during course selection in January, February after that evening and then go through the course selection process.
We'll connect with students to help facilitate the application and get that, you know, then there's an interview process and all that.
But we can help facilitate that in the spring.
There are also some career education workshops that we wanted to highlight available to parents.
Education Planner BC is the website that students will use when they apply to post-secondary when they're in grade 12.
And they also are hosting a parents as education and career coaches session this fall.
It's on Wednesday, November 12th, so in about a month.
And the links, you'll be able to click on the link in here and we'll probably send out some information as we get closer.
And that's open to anybody, any high school parent who wants to learn a bit more about this site.
The nice thing about Education Planner is it's a site you can apply to post-secondary on,
but you can also do some research about all the different schools that are available in BC that might be of interest to students.
And then we found this other cool one, you want to mention that?
Yeah, and I'll just mention about the Education Planner.
They're actually they host this career parents as career coaches session for different areas around the province.
And Burnaby's presentation is actually tonight at the exact same time this presentation is happening.
So the data I've given you is for the Coquitlam area and it will be the same information and it seemed the most relevant one.
So the other one is Success is Hope is holding a post-secondary education pathways forum.
That's on Thursday, November 6th.
That's at Burn Creek Community School.
Again, just another place for people who are looking for more information, want to get to be able to speak to some people, ask some questions,
find out what these paths look like to go ahead into post-secondary.
Again, we'll send out the registration.
We can send these all out by email as well.
Thank you. Thank you so much.
If anyone has any questions, we'll go answer questions.
Hold on.
OK, where are we?
Volunteer hours before grade 10 counted towards graduation.
So students can start collecting graduation hours May 1st to grade 10 until the end of grade 12.
Prior to May 1st to grade 10, then those hours would go towards getting a service award.
So any any volunteering that you do grade 8, 9, 10 is for service after May 1st, grade 10.
Then you can put those hours towards graduation.
They need to be done closer to graduation.
That's why.
And volunteering in the school definitely goes towards service award.
Some volunteering students do in the school is actually part of a course credit.
So the leadership is a requirement as part of the course.
So that is not really service. That is a course requirement.
But any other volunteering, it is a very simple form that students fill out and they can grab it from us in the Career Center.
I think.